addiction an externalized mechanism of
reward that is confused for necessity
something unmovable and unquestionable
a routine don't mean hit the conditions
in a Pavlovian circularity of
reinforcement and that then conditions
my very understanding of necessity and
truth and reality and compels me to act
in a certain way
there's a couple of things that come up
John Vevey keys framework of relevance
realization and salience landscaping in
the mind of the addict your salience
landscape is distorted right and what
what is relevant is that which is
relevant to your addiction to the
servicing of your addiction and so all
of the other stuff in the world the
volumes turned down on that and all the
stuff which feeds your addiction the
volume is turned up on all of that stuff
so it's it's profoundly distorting of
one's perception of reality and so one's
ability to discern what is meaningful
and truthful and right to do in that
landscape becomes impossible the
distortion of reality as something
heightened or privileged by addiction it
could be just a system of prioritization
because priorities also distort reality
is distort the volume that we put on
things
you
addiction is being linked to certain
forms of behavior and quite useful there
is a correlation that's been made with
behavior like gambling on the stock
exchange and addiction and those
physical rewards that one gets when
engaged in certain behaviors that means
that even certain legitimized forms of
distortion are incorporated into the
system like stock markets and stock
exchange yeah Gadwal masse defines
addiction as any behavior which provides
Solace or comfort and which cannot be
stopped even when one realizes it is
having detrimental effects on one's life
and so he sees it as usually a response
to trauma right it's a self-medicating
or self-tanners self palliating response
to trauma which then becomes a thing in
and of itself to be serviced so you have
rooted often in healing right it's it's
something which begins as self-healing
and then gets away gets away from you
after that and so the the truth of the
addiction actually changes over time
right it starts off as a legitimate and
functional adaptive response to a
circumstance in the environment but then
because the trauma is never dealt with
and healed the solution to it is held on
some becomes a trauma in and of itself
kind of thing the
to one's life what happens if it's a
detriment to someone else's life that is
an indirect proximity and going back to
that idea of the gambling on the stock
exchange it may not actually have a
detriment on my own life it may be
having a huge detriment to a lot of
other people but it has a dissociative
element that allows it to then take
place because the detriment isn't
directly fed into my own seeing of the
world and so I incorporate that into a
valid form of behavior a reality that's
acceptable to me
the counter-argument that would be that
it is actually detrimental to that
individual's life they just don't
realize it right because they're so
trapped in their delusion and so what it
is actually doing is blocking them from
having relationships with their family
and their friends and appreciating the
world for what it is and bla bla bla bla
bla
so they although they may not be
immediately aware of and connected to
the detriment it is still doing that if
it's if it's an addiction yeah the the
relationship between
truth and addiction is a very
interesting one because truth is the way
out of addiction right and addiction
clouds one's ability to perceive truth
so they are inextricably linked in that
sense this view of detriment to oneself
as being something that is because it
affects the fabric of our understanding
of social relationships is fascinating
because it can't be sufficient to divine
define addiction because otherwise any
antisocial behavior could be defined as
addictive if it's become a pattern
addiction there needs to be a sort of
strong compulsion that pushes you
towards something and it's complicated
not sure about all of that and then the
link to truth again it's this notion of
distortion and truth and how much
distortion actually equivalent some form
of questioning our reality or being
acceptable as a distortion compulsion is
definitely a part of it definitely a
part of that inability to not engage in
the behavior is definitely a part of it
and the dopamine hit is definitely a
part or some kind of internal reward if
not dopamine but but not some kind of
internal reward which is sought
definitely but yeah this this this link
between truth and addiction feels really
important because as I said before the
the way out of addiction is facing up to
the truth of it right understanding and
and being able to speak the truth of it
to other people is why programs like AAA
and scoob's are so effective
because their forums for that truth to
be expressed it's almost as if you have
these constructed maps of our world one
of them which is fueled by the
compulsion and dopamine or whichever
reward system is in place and the other
which has some form of externally
validated truth and the two plashing so
how to distinguish between how big that
difference has to be for it to be
socially acceptable or not for it to be
detrimental or not and that's where all
the fine lines come in of when someone
actually believes that they have an
addiction or not is how much it affects
the reading we have of the trees how
important this notion of the truth is
becoming in relationship to this one it
is maybe externally pacted and maybe
more socially constructed it does
socially value I like that phrase
socially validated truth I like does
that make it any more true though just
because it's socially validated I mean
that's that's a that's a trap as well
potentially isn't it that accepting
things as more true than your truth
simply because more people believe it to
be true that that doesn't feel quite
right either so yeah they're there for
yeah this is a minefield now right
especially in the mind of the addict
because you can't trust your own
perceptions of truth and group truth
isn't necessarily any better than
individual truth and so it's about
finding individuals and groups that yes
trust isn't it back to trust
transparency and Trust
how'd you develop trust when you're in
the maelstrom of addiction how on earth
do you distinguish who can be trusted
and who can't be it's a mess